hey push students let's cover everything
you need for period
[Music]
one before we start pronounce the speed
review sheet to help you follow along
with this video it's free and you can
find it linked in the description below
right now look at unit one Circle any
people events vocab things that you
might not quite remember that you know
you need to focus on as we review Once
you're confident that you've mastered a
topic you can check that one off and
then move on to the next one all right
here we go period one focuses on pre-con
Native American societies the colliding
the old world and the new world with the
Colombian Exchange and the focus of
European exploration it's one of the
shortest units at APUSH so you will
likely only see a few questions on the
exam period one starts with what we call
the pre-con Native American cultures
what were they like before the Europeans
ever got to the new world we're focused
strictly on North America and we
typically see this broken down into
specific regions it's important to
understand the geography in these
specific regions and how that influenced
the development of these cultures for
example in the Great Plains those tribes
were more nomadic whereas in the
Southeast they're more stationary
because as they're developing
agriculture tribes across North America
developed Advanced and unique societies
that were culturally and politically
complex the Aztec and Ina tribes along
with the Mayans are great examples of
this it's also really important to
understand the role that may is played
in a lot of these cultures it's not just
an agricultural staple for them but
they're using all parts such as the husk
or even the cob to help support their
societies but all this is really going
to change after the Spanish monarchs
Ferdinand and Isabella agree to sponsor
the Voyages of Christopher Columbus he
was originally looking for a route to
the East Indies and instead he ended up
in the Caribbean which is where we get
the Colombian Exchange this is where we
start to see the old world and the new
world come together Europe is going to
gain lots of new crops that came from
the new world such as maze tobacco and
potatoes the transfer of germs culture
religion and people are also part of the
Colombian Exchange but more importantly
are going to be the effects of the
Colombian Exchange the Native Americans
benefit from things like horses which
really helped with hunting and warfare
but they're going to be greatly affected
by the diseases like small poox and
measles that will decimate the native
populations and what we call the great
dine Europe on the other hand is going
to benefit with the introduction of all
these new resour ources they are going
to have population growth and be gaining
wealth and power during this time this
ability to gain wealth and power leads
to the pope supporting the Catholic
nations in Exploration with the Treaty
of toras this enabled Spain to dominate
in the new world taking over vast
territories while Portugal is building
and dominating in the African slave
trade with the support of both the
monarchy and the church the Spanish
conquistadors are now able to go out and
sege for gold God and Glory hernand
Cortez was one of the most famous kador
because he conquered the Aztecs and he's
also the one you're most likely to see
on your AP exam after often using
violence to subdue the indigenous
populations in these Latin American
territories the Spanish conquerors would
then subjugate them under systems like
inanda to make the Native Americans
extract the wealth from their land to
enrich the Spaniards the Catholic Church
also sent missionaries to these regions
to help convert the native population
Spanish power in the new world also led
to the development of the Costa system
where we see a racial hierarchy develop
because we starting to see a mix of the
races as we start to see the
introduction of African slaves to these
Spanish regions we'll see the
development of the ento system where
Africans were subjugated as well this
poor treatment of Native Americans by
the Spanish will lead to the valid deid
debates in Spain the stars of these
debates are Las Casas and seula who
argue over how the natives should
actually be treated by the Spanish in
the new world as a Dominican frier who
had been to the new world and was a
missionary Los cus supported better
treatment of the natives he wanted to
convert them to Catholicism but he
thought that they were complex
intelligent people that just needed to
be taught the proper way to do things
saula also thought the natives should be
converted to Catholicism but he
supported the encomendas ism because he
felt that the natives were barbaric and
unintelligent and incapable of learning
while there were many debates as to how
the Spanish should treat the natives
these two specifically are the ones
frequently referenced on the AP exam so
com examity what question should you be
prepared to answer for period one
questions you'll probably see something
about causes of exploration why are the
Spanish out here doing this you'll also
see questions about effects of the
Colombian Exchange we can also see
comparison questions for period 1
specifically comparing the various
Native American regions or comparing the
debates of lost costus since of pulva
when it came to treatment of the natives
check out the aush ultimate review
packet for more help we've got timeline
study guides and Essay practice follow
the link in the description below for a
free preview if you found this video
helpful please like And subscribe and
thanks for watching